say means the world the world
Loca and then again means uh Jewel or
ornament
like and again G is still on and master
my Lord my is still on the image of a
wish giving gem wish fulfilling Gem and
the idea is that a wish giving gem gives
its owner the most precious thing in the
world that they could wish
for the best thing in the world that
they could wish
for and the three jewels give people the
same thing in that they give them the
highest thing that they could ever get
which is normally we say uh Nirvana and
Enlightenment Nirvana and Enlightenment
those two things
so in that way the three jewels are like
a wish giving Jewel
also to me it kind of breaks down at the
wishing part though
why you just most people can't even
frame the concept of what they're going
to be you know most people can't even
imagine like if the wishing Gem of the
three jewels was limited to what you
could think of you'd be in trouble it's
beyond what you could think of but
beyond that it's a pretty nice you mean
okay CH means World ornament is that
what I become a world ornament sort of
you mean like a gem right for the whole
world in the sense that you give them
the highest things in the
world and if you said because you give
them the highest thing they could ever
wish for I think you can have a debate
you
see cuz they can't even frame the
idea uh one number five right
yes okay for
say
ch ch ch
um this is the choke and coin choke
right if you think about it the last
four have only been talking
about jewels or con really rare but here
they get the choke part the choke part
comes out in this one five um so choke
means infinitely Supreme the KN means
really really Supreme do Supreme of the
Supreme highest
Supreme and for this you need the story
of
The Chemical Bank
bankruptcy uh like at one point I had
all these uh gemology degrees and then
people would the Supreme Court of New
York Manhattan called me and said will
you testify on a a thing about jewels
you know and I said sure you know how
much
money okay and uh a company went
bankrupt uh a loan
company and um they had themselves
borrowed money before they went bankrupt
on the basis of having a whole safe
deposit box full of diamonds so they
borrowed so much money from the bank on
the basis of this box of diamonds so
then they went bankrupt so then the
Supreme Court calls me in and says will
you um assess the value of the diamonds
in the safe deposit box so I said yeah
but there's one thing they taught you in
galy school was I want a lawyer sitting
next to me to see if I switch anything
or anything goes wrong or you know they
teach you that you know so I said I want
so okay we had a lawyer and two lawyers
sitting next to me and we go down in the
basement of the chemical bank and um
they take out this like we go on the
Vault it's this huge thing and then they
take out the safe deposit box and they
put it on the table and I start going
through the I spread them out all the
gems diamonds on the table you put them
all top down then you pick them up with
these Special tweezers and you start
using this uh special eye glass and the
whole room is like quiet totally silent
like these people are wondering how much
they've been burned for if they've been
burned or you know how much is the loss
going to be you know and I'm like like
this you know and then he says uh what
do you think and I said they're all fake
oh my God 100% cubics are
comms you know and and I'm like thanking
jamaly school for telling me I have a
lawyer next to me you know uh
and and a funny thing happened uh the
lawyer came up to me afterwards he said
what are you going to do it what should
we do with those diamonds you know I
said throw them out they're worth 20
cents each 10 cents each you know and he
looks at me and he says could you make
me some earrings out of
this like okay you pay for the $20 gold
mounting I I'll put him in there you
know yeah my wife will love it you know
what I okay and so we made earrings for
every L you know that we fake and um com
with you but you know that feeling that
they got the moment I said cuum you know
the feeling that you're good that you
have a box full of useless taste nothing
you know uh that's what chug chug means
the real thing chug means the real thing
highest compared to fake highest
compared to uh fake
not the real thing okay money
intelligence Health uh Beauty friends
education uh military
power uh living in the best country it's
all fi just nothing means nothing okay
can't protect you at all you know people
found that out while we were in Retreat
right I think there's this huge wave
that we feel that you're don't know
about you know we see this wave you know
we see a wave that I don't think you can
really be aware of cuz you were in it
you know but those of us that in three
Retreat we see this way passing through
the world it's very strange and
malevolent way and it's this also this
feeling of uh Panic almost at a very
deep level and people are just
confronted with the fact that this are
not Refuge those big buildings and uh
all that economic power and military
power and security and
secure borders by two oceans and all
that is not um it doesn't that's not
security that's fi and these gems are
like the real thing the jewels are like
the real thing like they can protect you
they will protect you the knowledge of
emptiness and Karma and how to keep your
vals is the only thing that can protect
anybody period and the three jewels have
to help people learn that do that so you
have to think about
becoming real security for people real
security
you can offer people real security the
only real Security in the world is that
each one of us has the the newa right
the ability
to see that we can create the world
according to our what we do towards
others because the world is empty and
that's that makes you a real Refuge you
know that makes you you can really help
people of all the people like in Tucson
on October 10th
we we've been to the normal refuges we
went to the doctor we had X-rays we went
to the dentist we had our I check we
went to the bank we went to the post
office we went there's no refuge there
you know so for a short time uh a few
real refugees are going to be in Tucson
at the Y uh teaching and then you have
to like really get this text right and
you have to get this teaching right in
your mind and strong and then you become
a real refuge for somebody real
protection real service service
organization okay uh number six
I'm going to go way over today nobody
mind right okay
say
g g means to change g
means unchanging it's a common name in
the KAG tradition G would be a common
name good friend of mine
KAG unchanging I would translate it in
this context as unwavering
unwavering and J J says look if you have
one of those wish giving gems
uh it doesn't matter whether the owner
is nice to it or not right like it'll
still give you your wish like a wish
giving Jam is not like an Aladin lamp in
the te in the sense that the wish giving
Jam doesn't matter how you treat it like
you can call the wish giving gem a
dumbhead or you can call it a genius the
wish giving gem doesn't care right it
just gives you your
wishes just like that now you you
feeling the rest for me metaphor for
what three jewels don't care you can
abuse the three jewels as much as you
want they will still do all they can to
help you okay they're unwavering in that
sense okay they don't care whether you
to say something nice to them or whether
you try to diss them or anything like
that and as you become more and more of
a teacher then you'll find that you'll
have to develop this quality okay like
there are everybody's you are empty
everybody will have a different
perception totally based on their own
Karma
so you will be perceived differently by
every student you ever have and
throughout history that's always been
the case Lord Buddha was the victim of
several assassination attempts yeah we
St we spoke about his Holiness
um has been the the object of
uncountable assassination attempts and
um that's just the way it happens people
will perceive you differently and some
will treat you good and some will treat
you bad but you have to be G men and
then later when you become one of the
three Jo you're really gar man in that
you don't care you just keep serving
keep helping keep doing what other
people need no matter how they treat you
that's and that's one of the qualities
of one of the three
jeels G thrs in something else you know
three Jews especially Dak is G in
another
sense like
what it's TAA meaning unchanging meaning
yeah because it's
emptiness not because it's empty care
yeah you're get a
BCT yeah so emptiness so so g j being g
j being one of the greatest Debaters in
tibetan history says yeah but don't
forget it we want to become your man in
the sense of being the
dhakai pure emptiness sheer
emptiness and when you see you know the
story I told you many times when you see
empty this directly
you come out of it and you realize that
the end you saw includes the dhak of the
budha you've met in that sense you've
met the Buddha you confirm the existence
of a Buddha by meeting that emptiness
directly
okay
uh oh there's a little section where
um G of J discusses the idea of cause
refuge and result Refuge
and I just thought we should it's in
course number two I think yeah but I
thought I'd throw in what he says so
we're going to go a little
bit
for for
[Music]
say again those of you studying to B and
you see the prenasal here which is
because of this um
okay and it just got corrupted in modern
so I want you to be able to speak it
properly if theet met you and you said
if you said it would sound funny to them
say
and would say
what ch ch the would say
SK Mong would say
SK
[Music]
okay just
uh here yeah yeah
yeah
in which is the right one
right
okay David k
um and as I said Michael when we were
talking about in class I always get
mixed up about which is which this is
cause Refuge cause going for Refuge Jo
means to go you means cause means
protection or Refuge okay causal going
for
Refuge to remember if you want a trick
for remembering it you are going for
Refuge to the cause of your
Enlightenment which is other people you
understand I mean just people outside of
you like like shakuni Buddha who's
already Buddha they're going to cause
you to get Enlighten that's the way I
remember it okay can be confusing you're
going for Refuge to the cause meaning
someone who can teach you what to do to
get light
yourself then de de means result de
means result and that's the
opposite going for cause in the result
of your own efforts to get in light
which
is yourself as a Buddha in the
future and just as a practical uh
exercise and I'm suggesting that at the
YMCA or those of you who teach this in
other places like South Africa or
whatever that you might want to during
the whole series of lectures get people
to do uh meditation in which they
are focusing on the omnicient being that
they are to become watching them
focusing on the ommission being that
they are to become it's a very
interesting exercise Winston the Buddha
if you're not a Buddha already I don't
know is watching this class at this
moment because they see all three times
at the same moment right so Winston the
Buddha is watching Winston studying
about Winston the Buddha who's going to
watch Winston
[Music]
and to me that's very powerful like I
can sit by myself alone in my room
sometimes and I'll open a book and I'll
just look up and I'll say I'm working on
it you know and like sometimes I talk to
myself who's watching me you know and
it's a very powerful exercise you know I
mean then people think you're really
crazy you know it's another thing on
your list of why you're crazy
right but it can be very powerful you
just sit quietly you can go out walk
down near the water spring and you can
just sit there and talk to the booty
you're going to be say you know uh
you're probably laughing at all the
stupid stuff I'm doing right now you
probably mad at me because I didn't get
there as fast as I was supposed to and
maybe you could just send me a
few ways of help like Grace inspiration
you know help me out here I'm trying you
know and sometimes I justed do that I
just talk cuz they're watching I'm
watching me right already
so yeah so every single being in this
room could be an elimination of my
future that's true too she said
everybody in this room could be
anination of my future yes I don't know
we have to talk that's a debate for the
debate the only reason I bring this up
is that there's a neat little part in
GJ's commentary where he says look uset
llamas didn't make this idea up okay we
didn't make this up this is Tau in
Tantra and it that comes from an ancient
scripture called the sura requested by
UGA this is where the result and cause
of refugees okay yeah like he says to
like to do this in the early scriptures
they're like like we didn't make this
out this comes from India because to
them India was the place at the AR
right you know they said we didn't make
this out this idea comes from the
ancient scriptures it's found in the
Tantra and it comes from the Sut
requested by the I think it's a body Nam
ug do in tibetan okay and then g j
quotes that scripture and I've uh put it
in your reading if you ever get it and
I'm still working on the first reading
it's really long it's like turned out
like 25 pages but it was fun and
um in that I want to tell you about that
Sutra what what the ug UGA is called
kimd kimd means householder it means
this POA was not a mon and um this this
lay person named ugar asked Lord Buddha
uh what how do we take refuge you know
what is it like when you say you say we
should take refuge what is it to take
refuge and Lord Buddha says abodh SATA
who is a householder right and he's
specifically talking about normal people
right he's saying but any buddhis first
he says budh sapper and then he says
specifically Bon sappa to our
householders late people he says you see
the marks of a Buddha you see what I
look like right he says right I see and
then he
says the moment you just get in your
mind I would like to be like you you
know I would like to be like you and you
you you see yourself in the future like
me you've taken Refuge that's Refuge
that's taking refe you said to me that's
very beautiful say that's the source for
this teaching because really you got
both in there don't you you have
and you're looking at
a you're seeing what they look like and
what they do and then because of that
you're taking ja you're imagining what
you're going to be like and you're
wanting to be like that so the
desire which which involves which
implies imagining yourself as a Buddha
in the future to become a Buddha as you
look at the Buddha is what it means to
take refuge and to me that's very
powerful it's not
like was it what did we hear where was
that
place how'd it
go we were in travesty we met some teron
and how' it go that little
[Music]
tune and then it went this beautiful s
you know but just to sit there and think
about an image of Lord Buddha or you
know that's not it in that scripture it
specifically STS you are visualizing
what you will become and that's taking
refuge and I love that I think that's
really neat it's almost tantric in a way
okay okay you on the last question but
you don't know it has six parts
we finished now the I mean we talked
about the seven Diamond Visions as a
whole and then we talked about the first
three as a whole meaning the three
jewels now we start in the process of
going through them one by one we go
through the seven one by one um
that will take the rest of the course
and it takes the rest of the utar Tantra
okay I don't think I mentioned I
mentioned and I didn't finish
it the first
four of the seven Diamond
Visions are the subject of the first
chapter which order of the seven Diamond
Vision first order the first order right
meaning budha dharm and then come your
Buddha nature that's why the first
chapter is called the chapter
on Buddha nature yeah it's called the
chapter of Buddha nature it's
interesting that my CH did that he
didn't make it seven chapters he made it
shorter so somehow your future
buddhahood your future dharmah Hood your
future s hood and your ability to become
that your potential to become that he
all he CHS them all in one chapter so
the first chapter is like half the
book then he does the next three of the
diamond Visions which are number
three yeah buddhahood outside you uh you
intend you intend the qualities of the
Brotherhood and then CH meaning the most
important quality which is that they can
come here and teach you okay
activity so those form the second third
and fourth chapters of the book but I
forgot to tell you I think there's a
fifth chapter he's through in a fifth
chapter and it's just called penion Shea
it means explaining the benefits I
didn't read it yet it probably means a
small chapter where he explains the
benefits of this book or something like
that but just so you know there's five
chapters like that um explaining the
benefits yeah it's just called the
chapter on explaining the benefits which
they often throw into books to sell them
to people but I don't know why I put at
the end but anyway
uh now we're going to talk about the S
The Jewel of the Buddha the Buddha Jewel
now we're on to the first of the seven
and that's what we're going to do the
rest of
today and we're going to go through the
six qualities that that Buddha Jewel has
so we already did six qualities of
what the three jewels in general now
we're going to six qualities of the
Buddha jeel in
particular and this is a very very
famous verse from the utar Tantra it's
often quoted in the monastic textbooks
like all over the place like this is one
verse that everybody would
learn you know she has a milary and you
you quote that all the time in the
monastery so I thought I'm trying to
emphasize the quotations that are most
and the ideas that are most used in an
actual monks training from the utar
Tantra again we don't study utar Tantra
separately uh we study
abisa for 12 years but but the utar
comes up a lot so here's one of the most
famous this versus
and hang in there it's kind to going to
go long today and maybe it's a little
warm but uh we have to work like this or
we'll never get things done so sorry for
about this kind of thing we have to go
late and
um and you have to work hard and get it
on the first TR you know like you have
to go home and really work on it cuz if
you wait till the end uh which is one
week before the October classes you
probably won't be able to teach very
well okay so if you start planning box
CHS now they'll be all fresh by time
they'll start sprouting by October say
do my CH do my
CH d as we said before
means unproduced unchanging unproduced
yeah you say unproduced unproduced
by the way there's a translation they
use
un what they called
un no they saying un uncomposed or
something like that that's completely
wrong okay just throw that translation
out they say uncomposed or something if
they misunderstood the meaning of do do
much again s okay so don't space is
composed of Parts but it's unchanging
see so that's a bad translation but
anyway
um d means unproduced meaning doesn't
have causes doesn't mean it never
happened right obviously D much implies
that the thing already exists but it did
not have a cause it's always it's either
always been there or it's not caused in
the sense that there are not energies
put into it which fluctuate it's always
the same it's always the same do much CH
to understand this we need to talk
about what you're going to be like when
you become a Buddha okay so
me the
Buddha you got to think like that you
know like when you do yoga you have this
idea about how you're going to look at
the end right maybe uh and when you
study this class you should have this
idea of what you're going to be like so
we're going to go through what you be
like you're going to have mainly two
different bodies which just means two
different parts of you okay which are
what nice uh let's call it the truth
body I call it dharm body here that's
me and the form body
and you know there's three ways of I
mean you can divide the bodies of three
you can divide them into four we're
doing it two
today and the entire T is one of the
places where you see all those
divisions um D Body itself can be
divided into two anybody want to take a
shot EMP yeah the emptiness
and I'm
Miss oh let's call
with emptiness means
I'm
sorry I'm going to change
this we call it Essence
body which
is this one is changing or unchanging
the
wisdom changing changing every moment I
mean when you see somebody making
pancakes 2,000 years from now you know
and the bubble comes out to the top the
wisdom
changes the image in the mind changes
when the bubble comes up and Pops
there's two different images therefore
this mind is changing okay you're seeing
it at the same time aren't you yeah you
do see it all at the same time even
changing more
again that's a huge debate in huge
debate
is there change in a Buddhist perception
but the change is is a phenomenon also
right so they perceive them but if you
think about at any given time you're
seeing all the stuff in the universe It
Ever Was is and will be always the same
well at the same time but their time
frame is changing from our point of view
but that's another Point anyway ence's
body is is Purity they call it Purity d
means Purity Purity in the sense of
being devoid of something okay two kinds
of words of
something natural and
achieved natural and achieved
got it now let's go back to the first
quality of Buddha by the way we now have
uh down at the bottom now we have
one and
two we have
three of the six qualities of a Buddha
the first three
relate to this
side the first three relate to the
Dharma body okay of the six quality of
the Buddha Jewel that you will
become the first three relate to the
Dharma
body of the six qualities of the Jewel
of the Buddha that you will become
secondary relate to the form body
and roughly roughly roughly it's
so in debate you always start with
roughly or most of the time or mostly
and then you don't get in trouble when
somebody comes up with an exception you
say oh I started I said roughly okay but
roughly this whole side of your Budd
Hood accomplishes the ultimate needs
of
yourself this side of your whole
buddhahood is the accomplishment of your
own ultimate goals which means that the
other side is the ultimate
accomplishment of others goal which
makes sense right you need to take form
to help other
beings okay very few beings can perceive
a Buddha directly right I mean how many
people can see the dharmakaya
directly you got to be an iron you got
to be an iron or have to have been an
iron
right and and when there's a debate at
the end of the first reading I threw it
in they're debating what kind of were n
as and M first level third level 10th
level there's an argument about it the
point is it's that rare it's that rare
maybe there have been three irons in
Indian Buddhism something like that I
mean you have
to realize that it's that kind of thing
okay
um so to really take care of finish your
own needs you have to have a d body to
really take care of other people's needs
you have to be able to emanate a form
body the Essence body is the emptiness
half of the dhak okay The Emptiness of
of of a
Buddha in a in a sense that's the most
important why how could you why would
you might why would it might be
appropriate to even call it
Ki tough question why would it almost be
a to call this emptiness of the Buddha K
you have to have very good seeds in your
mind to be able to see that Buddha
that's you could say that but Foundation
of everything else what would what would
a c what would a
things and it's good it's true
I it's the source of it it's really The
Source if you think about it it goes
back to what we said that we when we
started today my see perfect students
for this course perfect students for
this class the only kind of students
that would be interested in sitting out
the desert in this class for 4 hours or
however long it's going to take right uh
they got to have what was I getting on
to they have to understand that it's
emptiness that makes it up NAA it's the
possibility that to become enlightened
and really that's emptiness so this
becomes crucial this particular
emptiness becomes
crucial actually you should call this
voidness and I'll tell you why later
well I'll tell you right now okay this
is a kind of voidness of Purity but it's
a voidness in two senses one is natural
voidness one is achieved
voidness natural purity and achieved
Purity what's the difference between
natural purity and achieved Purity
natural purity is the Purity you've had
all along it's the Buddha nature you
have right now it's the yess of your
body and mind it's the availability for
you to become anything in the
universe as soon as you start keeping
your vve book and your morning
meditation
and do your three
Retreats we'll miss you but we'll cook
for you say that one more time we'll
miss you but we'll cook for
you I like that part natural
purity refers
to yeah the natural voidness that You'
always had the emptiness of your that
doesn't change from the beginningless
time up to now up until your doesn't
change that comes with you and that's
the only reason you become that's
connected back to that idea of potential
or possibility that we talked about NAA
because you recognize that you are a
true student for this text this teaching
what would an achieve Purity
be it's like the work you've done to
clean out your negativities abandoning
St yeah like getting rid of your
negativities the absence of doubt in the
mind of an audient would be an example
once you've seen emptiness directly you
can't doubt these
scriptures anymore not you know you'd go
crazy about them that's
achieved but again it's sort of it's an
absence of something right so these two
natural and achieved Purity are still an
absence of
something and then wisdom is just
uh I I should call this
wisdom is what we call jwa
by the way we're not Crossing this line
I just didn't have any place to put it
it's still over here on the Dak side
okay you can divide the understanding
that you will have as a br right you can
divide it into two parts Anda
say
andaa is kind of hanging out over here
okay I don't know how spell
that I think is
yeah say cha
gwa means the the ability of an
enlightened being to see the true nature
of all existing things the true nature
of all existing
things means how they are means how they
are the way they
are that's nice but you also need the
ability
what to see all those things themselves
that's a big difference it's one thing
to to see all the things in the kitchen
it's another thing to see the true
nature of all the things in the kitchen
okay that's what refers to the true
nature yeaha means seeing all the things
in the
kitchen means seeing the true nature of
all the things in the
kitchen belongs on the dharmakaya side
and in this presentation only okay Geva
is thrown in with the form body
side okay the ability to see all the
things in the universe is thrown over
here with the form body side which if
you think about it for one minute you
can figure out why he did that
Thea is body but not thewa gwa is over
here on the dharmakaya
side
yeah because Geneva is seeing all the
things in the
universe is seeing all their emptinesses
all that you why he does that we'll talk
about now we're ready to find out why
the six are called the six
back so we said do my man unproduced
unproduced why are you going to be
unproduced when you're a
Buddha Al because
yourist which
one great quality number one is hanging
out right here that's why I did this
whole silly chart
okay the fact that you are still empty
when you get in
LED in fact that that's why you can be a
Buddha at that point is it is the Ki the
foundation of everything you are anyway
is is your natural emptiness the one
you've had all along that's the first
quality of the six that you're going to
have when you get nine going to
have no debate you're not going to
debate had it from the already have it
come
on oh so you already have that
natural
purity du good good uh
that's how
say you still have that you already have
the natural purity
right which used to say you already have
come
right which us to say you already
have which is to say you already have
the seed which is going to turn into a
Buddha so a Buddha has a which is going
to turn into a
[Music]
Buddha so Buddha doesn't have Buddha
nature good so Buddha doesn't have
common cuz you said they were the
same you said they were the
same get somebody in trouble that way
okay go over the video you'll figure it
out okay just kidding K when I phrase it
as see to become a
Buddha right yeah uh then you get in
trouble then you got to be wait a minute
you're talking about the buha which
still has impurities remember that thing
yeah yeah come then he said which C you
talking about you know you got to be
careful the whole point of debate is to
get somebody on to you know they say
that and then he goes for it and then
he's like in trouble you jump yeah okay
okay second
quality so this natural purity
is abandon that buddh hood oh good
de
I well if the natural purity is to Cal
and that defined as
one's nature surrounded by impurity is
it the come well if it's Purity it can't
be impure
right yeah so can it be calm if it's
pure uh the question is is is it exactly
equal to
come no I don't think so right I don't
think so
yeah but you have to debate
it okay
say L key
enough
time
[Music]
say
short like l in this is the meaning of
that name means
spontaneous means happen like in
a just means you know means happen
means you know just means happen like
that it refers to the spontaneous
ability of enlightened being to go and
reach all other beings and help
them no
premeditation not even any dis cursive
or conceptual
thought no idea I have to go to planet
Earth now and help those people you just
appear there automatically sometimes I
like to translate hung d as
automatically okay
automatically do you want to debate me
on
something she look like I'm waiting for
somebody let's go back
here nothing raises a
question huh which side of the road is
yeah it's on the wrong side I said the
first three we're going to be on the
left side left side this one's got to be
on the right side I blessed my brain
about this all
morning then I read G more
carefully and it's very beautiful
there's a very very very
subtle mental Affliction all right you
almost can't call it a mental Affliction
but at the very very final stages of
your how just before you get enlightened
you you get rid of and an extremely
subtle B
Chun that infects
um your mind just when you think to do
something the intention to do something
like the idea to move my arm from here
to here right there's some kind of
trigger thought in my mind there's some
kind of impulse impulse thought in my
mind and there's something very very
subtly self-existent about I very very
subtle extremely subtle it's called like
one of the final negativities that you
ever remove on the way to Budd when you
remove that you can consider
yourself uh
purified that can be considered
achieving achieved
purification I'll say it again when you
get rid of the very very subtle seeds of
seeing things that self existent that
infect the decision to act
itself you reached what we call achieved
Purity when you get rid of that final
one we can say that you have the
achieved Purity meaning the one you had
to work for as opposed to
the natural
purity okay got it I'll say it one more
time I'll say it one more
time apparently what the most
final self-existent thought you have one
of the last ones is the self-existence
which infects the decision to act to do
anything like just even to to to pick up
a pen and the decision to to say a word
there's something very
subtly more let's say you're more
vulnerable to seeing things things as
self-existent the moment you decide to
act
now you can debate that a lot and you
can have a lot of wrong ideas about that
does it imply that we shouldn't think to
act doesn't imply that we shouldn't act
you know we've got to be really careful
about
that I think one of the mental
afflictions that could infect you at the
final moments is the belief that I am uh
picking up the
pen uh whole cause and effect thing
don't cause affect me like I go to the
dentist to fix my tooth is that what fix
my tooth no you see I make I drive to
tuon 4 hours ding B 5 hours to have some
guy drill my tooth is that what fixes my
tooth so I make a decision to get in the
car I make a decision to start the car I
make a decision to go that whole process
is infected by the Bel that it's the DST
is fixing my
tooth okay very subtle EX extremely
subtle it infects everything we do is
the way to get negative people out of my
life to avoid
them you see is that the way to get rid
of the people around me that that hurt
me or or who are irritating to me you
see it's it's all wrapped up in
worldview
so once you get rid of that final SE of
thinking could do anything for
self-existent reasons you no longer get
in the car because you believe the
dentist is self-existent going to fix
your teeth okay then you achieve a kind
of
Purity it's not a purity that you've
had all alone or
natural where is it
here here okay but it's spontaneous too
well it's spontaneous in that nature in
that
sense you see
so g j saying if you want to
know why Lord mraa didn't stick
spontaneous help of others over
here it's because when he said
spontaneous he was talking about doing
things with ultimately pure World
viiew they achieved
Purity the voidness of the final wrong
idea is so beautiful it's really
beautiful of course spontaneously
helping others belongs over here but in
the sense that it involves the final
understanding that things are empty it
belongs over here and that's where he
puts it
okay that's a tough point you got to go
over that I mean it's exciting point but
you got to go over it okay
okay third one
we got to move some of
those appointments
after
yeah I just want to roll through these
and not worry about how L it's going to
okay I never know when I write a class
how long it's going to take to teach it
okay better than
L okay
I'm also shortening them a bit to make
it
easier say shenen Shen to sh
sh Shen means other like exchanging self
and
[Music]
other Factor as opposed to the main
cause like contributing
cause with means
what realiz without the it means what
wrong idea careful yeah be very careful
without the s means wrong idea with the
s means right idea talk is wrong idea
and the pronunciation is exactly the
same yeah here it means right idea
realization right so when you debate you
got to be damn careful with
this guy lead you on for 20 minutes and
then suddenly tell you oh I was spilling
without the
sun covers himself either way right it's
very cool but it can be very confusing
we're reading a text which is badly
types that and the guy leaves out the
sus sometimes and it's really trouble
mean
means not okay so what do we got so far
not realized through the factor of a n
not realized through the factor of
another this is referring to a Buddha's
wisdom and specifically their ability to
see the true nature of all things this
is referring to a Buddhist wisdom and
specifically their ability to see the
true nature of all things let's go back
to that
chart where you going to put
that having to do with wisdom
yeah over
here you
know the wisdom which Peres The
Emptiness of all objects
that wisdom
is
okay not
realized through an influence of another
not realized through the influence of
another that has two meanings who wants
to take a shot at one of them
there's another
[Music]
one it's very
beautiful that thing can only be
described by the person who has seen
it huh yeah but in what way you direct
perception me but where is the other
coming it's not something you can
realize through influence of the other
meaning what the person yeah it's
Indescribable it's
Juda
Indescribable uh like a person who has
seen it directly can describe it to you
there's in fact y has a big debate about
whether you can describe it he says
Indescribable means can't be described
right the guy says right so say nobody
can describe it right just right this
Lord V didn't write 4,000 scriptures
right
you know so this sh you can't get thr B
but not it's not like someone can tell
you and then you just see it directly
that's impossible okay so in that
sense the ability of a Buddha to see the
true nature of all things cannot occur
through the influence of another person
it's not like someone can tell you what
it's like and then you can just boom do
it
okay but then G says Shen can also refer
to discursive thought discursive
perception where you are making forming
words in your mind where you're using
mental words mental sentences to
perceive this thing oh you know like
that it has to be
what can't be it has to be direct
nondescript ncri totally direct
communion with
emptiness
247 towards every object that ever was
is and will be so that's sh other
discursive yeah so g j says Shen can
mean two things other can mean another
guy but other can mean other than direct
perception meaning words mental words
using one
okay now we're on to the three qual I
think we should take a break
what is any need would you guys rather
go on and finish or would you rather
take a break
and at least one person wants to go on
and not take a break so let's go on I'll
try to do it a little
faster uh we're on to the three
qualities that relate
to yeah which is helping mainly other
people right oh these are know in my
head okay
uh what's he call it hang on
yeah I know okay
say Kima kimim
kimim if you don't know other people are
suffering or if you can't see all the
beings in the universe who are suffering
then you can't help them right so first
you have to have Kima Kima means
knowledge Kima means
knowledge well we'll talk about it
like like we didn't know that the world
transgender was blown up right and
so we didn't have Kima about all the
people who got killed or hurt and it was
some our friends you know and
um so we couldn't undertake any actions
to help them cuz we just didn't
perceived them saying we didn't know
that people were hurt we didn't know
that that anyone needed help so one of
the first qualities you're going to need
to be a good Buddha jewel is K about all
the people in the universe who are
suffering you got to have that now if
you happen to divide the knowledge of a
Buddha into that which the true nature
of all the things in the kitchen that's
what you perceived all the things in the
kitchen where would you put this
one that would
beun
Jun no now I'm talking about all the
things in the
kitchen all the s of beings who are
suffering not their true nature would be
where yeah I'm sorry j I'm sorry I'm
sorry you're right there we get number
four that's why he stuck G over with
what for body yeah even no it's not
physical it's mental okay but that's why
we throw it in over there okay we should
probably curve this dotted line over
here
right I mean that belongs over here so
we covered number
four what Geva means is all existing
objects the wisdom which can perceive
all existing objects genius all the
stuff in the kitchen all conventionally
existing object oh wait I'm gonna debate
you don't don't sorry it's really a good
debate you
know but B they didn't hear
uh all the things in the kitchen all
right the ability to see all the things
in the kitchen and gal has the ability
to see The Emptiness of all the things
in the kitchen but more specifically g
means the ability to see every existing
arle G sorry G yeah now ready for debate
Michael you
[Music]
want let's
take which perceives
all does it perceive all existing
objects you can
say and
disagree so it does receive all existing
objects right
[Music]
so so I guess doesn't exist Shin doesn't
exist right I didn't say that oh oh so m
is not I didn't say that Al is an
object yes but it doesn't belong to all
object yes it does oh so G is so G
also I didn't say
that so J doesn't see all existing
object I didn't say that so J does see
all existing objects as defined yes so
poor en doesn't get to be all existing
in the group of all existing
objects in this case no oh that's a
pretty good answer but it just happens
to be that the way g j FES that was the
different way then you ped it he said
look
obviously this Gena sees all the objects
in the
obviously The Emptiness of all the
objects in the universe is an object in
itself so obviously Gena does see what
is but it's a nice division anyway so
what the division made there's not a I
mean mostly we describe this as
perceiving The Emptiness of all the
things in the kitchen mostly we describe
this as perceiving all the things in the
kitchen but actually technically this
proceedes all the things in the kitchen
which includes the object
all right no fun you guys are no
fun all so we've covered four
right fine
and you should always put this shade
after a word
just that's the way it's done
say means love or concern
concern okay love or
concern and this is the way the logic
goes in the modern monastic scriptures
you know for one thing if you didn't
know that all these people got hurt you
can't you can't help them or you can't
feel any concern for them right so first
you have to have a perception of all the
people who got hurt right Kima number
four you have to know that there's
people who are hurting either through
direct or indirect means you have to
perceive that every single living
creature in the universe is
suffering but if you don't have C you
won't want to do anything
a okay that's the logical progression
love love care concern you have to think
to do something you know you have to be
concerned you have to be
concerned you have to want to do
something that's so which side would we
throw it in on rup d
that's interesting does it go over here
there so love is part
of what do you mean
by come on he's the lawyer get
it it's good for a deat um Gandhi is the
greatest law
right so means Abraham Lincoln yeah it's
love meaning oh so we can throw it on
over on the physical side of things in
the sense that you got to have love to
want to emate All the
Right
but it's no use to
have to know what's happening and to
care about it if you don't have
sh we had a new before
today right which was understanding the
possibility of the
power this is a different new this one
is
sh okay meaning what energy yeah energy
or power it's no use if you have Z if
you know that everyone's in trouble it's
no use if you have which is what I
forgot anyway
now if you don't what
is I don't
know
oh the Sans for this SE
is which is a little bit different from
n which is
K so just so you know the number five
was karun which is a little different
okay your s good teach go over that but
shy power it's no good to know that
everybody in the World Trade Center was
her it's no good to even be concerned
about it if you can't do anything about
it and you can help them even now if you
understand D you can help them even now
if you understand okay but mainly this
is talking about if you can't see all
that all being and the are
suffering you can't help them if you
don't care that they're suffering even
after you know that they're suffering
that doesn't count either but if you
have power shy if you have the power to
do something about it then you're a
real Buddha Refuge Buddha je Refuge then
you can help people then you are a
shelter then you are protected so really
we all have
to Aspire to those six qualities and you
got to think about them all the time you
got to think you know I'm going to have
this quality this quality this quality
this chart has to be in your mind I want
all six of those qualities I'm going to
have all six of those
qualies and under here you can put knows
what's going
on cares about what's going
on can't do something about what's going
on okay knows what's going on cares
about what's going on can do something
about what's going on
okay you want to have all six qualities
you should go home you should think
about getting those six qualities
becoming a Buddha Jew becoming the thing
that every Buddhist in the world is
taking refuge
in and even when people never heard of
Buddhism you'll become their Refuge you
will emanate as a suie saint or you will
emanate as the is sitting there next to
them on the bus who irritates them or
whatever it takes according to their
come
okay that's all uh so we'll finish there
I'm sorry I went on so long and uh see
you on
uh
Wednesday yeah at which time we'll
probably go over
the dad the next of the seven right okay